Guide to the John W. Taylor Papers 1798-1852 MS 615
New-York Historical Society
John W. Taylor Papers
1798-1852
New-York Historical Society
Taylor, John W., 1784-1854
MS 615
3.75 Linear feet
John W. Taylor (1784-1854) served as a United States Congressman from 1813-1833 and was appointed Speaker of the House twice. This collection is primarily correspondence from many of Taylor's contemporaries to him illuminating his role as a statesman particularly as to his leadership of the Restrictionist cause to abolish slavery in the newly developing western territories.
Arrangement Note
The John W. Taylor Papers are arranged both alphabetically and chronologically.
Missing Title
Series 1: Correspondence
Series 2: Speeches
Series 3: Governmental Documents
Series 4: Financial Documents
Series 5: Personal Papers
Biographical / Historical Note
Timeline for John W. Taylor
1784 Son of Judge John Taylor John W. Taylor born March 26, 1784 in Charlton, New York
1799 Enrolled at Union College at 15 years of age
1803 Member of Phi Beta Kappa Graduated Union College
1803-1807 Studied law with Samuel Cook Founded and taught at The Ballston Centre Academy
1807 Earned credentials as Attorney at Law in New York State
1810 Earned credentials as Counselor of Law in New York State
1811 Appointed Deputy Post Master of Hadley, Saratoga Country, New York
1812-1813 Served as New York State Commissioner of Loans Served in the New York State Assembly
1813-1833 Elected at 29 years of age for 10 consecutive terms to Congress as the House Representative from Saratoga County
1820-1821 Served as Speaker of the House for the 16th Congress
1825-1827 Served as Speaker of the House for the 19th Congress
1827 Became a member of the New-York Historical Society
1840-1842 Served in the New York State Assembly
1842 Suffered a paralytic stroke Moved to daughter's home in Cleveland, Ohio
1854 Died September 18, 1854 in Cleveland, Ohio at 70 years of age Buried in Ballston Spa, New York
Historical Context:
Described as a man who advocated "measures and not men... actions and not words", John W. Taylor was as much a product of his times as he was a creator of them, generating a legacy which while lacking direct recognition nevertheless permeates the American socio-political landscape in seminal and enduring ways. His papers reflect a deep and abiding commitment to service to his country, his constituents and his personal convictions.
Raised in an established American family with roots in Saratoga County, New York dating to 1692, Taylor distinguished himself early as a gifted student and debater. Upon graduation from Union College at the age of 19, he founded the Ballston Academy, engaged in successful business ventures, served as the Deputy Post Master and earned his law credentials. He married a young woman of Scottish descent, Jane Hodges, with whom he raised 5 sons and 3 daughters. Appointed to the State Assembly in 1811, Taylor's steady independence propelled him to federal office in 1813 as a Republican Congressman. Thus at the age of 29, Taylor joined a group of young, ambitious men including Henry Clay, Daniel Webster and John C. Calhoun who wrestled with the nuances of the physical, legal, political and spiritual governance of a county only just evolving from its infancy toward its first toddling steps as an individualized political entity.
John W. Taylor entered the national political arena during the second half of the War of 1812 in which the United States failed to extend its territory into Canada but succeeded in establishing itself as a militarily stalwart and politically autonomous country. Thus ensconced in President James Monroe's Era of Good Feeling, purported as a time of national unity while the country strove to expand, it was James Tallmadge, Jr. and Taylor, both congressmen from New York State, who in 1819 ushered the debate of the abolitionist into the goal of western expansion.
Championing the Restrictionist cause was an ethical imperative for Taylor who fervently promoted and authored amendments aimed at preventing and/or limiting the legally sanctioned institution of slavery into newly created states. Using his considerable parliamentarian talents as a tactful, fluent, concise and effective orator, Taylor's response to southern Secessionists threats was resolute: "The honorable gentleman greatly mistakes the people of this country if he supposes this Union, cemented by strong interests, consecrated by glorious achievement, sanctified by the blood of heroes, and endeared by victories won by the exertion and treasure of all … can ever be destroyed or in the least impaired by promoting the cause of humanity and freedom in America".
The results were variable often highlighting yet another seminal and enduringly contentious issue regarding the extent of the power of the Constitution as well as that of the federal government to dictate legislation upon States. Ultimately, many of Taylor's unsuccessful but core proposals formed the bedrock of the ensuing Missouri Compromises including the establishment of a geographic boundary between slave and free states at the 36/30 parallel known as the Mason-Dixon Line.
John W. Taylor went on to serve as Speaker of the House twice, during the second half of the 16th Congress in 1821 and again for the entire 19th Congress of 1825-1827. A statesman who advocated service to the people above service to a political party, his reluctance to be drawn into the contentious fractioning within the New York State Republican party between the Bucktails led by Martin Van Buren and the supporters of Governor DeWitt Clinton with whom Taylor was ultimately associated nearly cost him the 1821 appointment. By 1825, the machinations required to maintain political footing on the national stage had aligned Taylor solidly with long time ally John Quincy Adams in whose 1825 election Taylor provided pivotal support.
During the years of 1833-1842, intervening his Congressional Service and incapacitation from a paralytic stroke, Taylor returned to Saratoga County where he practiced law, served in the State Assembly and was instrumental in the development of the Whig party. Taylor spent his waning years in Cleveland, Ohio in the care of his daughter. He was buried upon his death at age 70 in Ballston Spa. Despite an absence of 12 years, his memorial at the courthouse was well attended by dignitaries and citizens of every ilk and he was eulogized as a man who "was lauded when he flourished and strengthened when he fainted, as scarce ever was a man before."
Historical Resources:
Alexander, DeAlva Stanwood. "John W. Taylor." Quarterly Journal of the New York State Historical Association 1 (January 1920): 14-37.
Booth, John Chester. Excerpt from Booth's History of Saratoga County, New York: 1858. Eds. Violet B. Dunn & Beatrice Sweeney. Saratoga County Bicentennial Commission, 1977. 11 December 2009 http://www.townofcharlton.org/CHS/highlightshistory.html
Johnson, William R. "Prelude to the Missouri Compromise: A New York Congressman's Effort to Exclude Slavery from Arkansas Territory." New-York Historical Society Quarterly 48 (January 1964): 31-50.
Spann, Edward K. "The Souring of Good Feeling: John W. Taylor and the Speakership Election of 1821." New York History 41 (October 1960): 379-399.
Sylvester, Nathaniel Bartlett and Cornelius E. Durkee. Excerpt from History of Saratoga County, New York: with illustrations and biographical sketches of some of its prominent men and pioneers. Philadelphia: Evert & Ensign, 1878. Interlaken, New York: Hearts of the Lakes Publishers, 1979. www.ancestory.com 11 December 2009 http://www.rootsweb.ancestry.com/~nysarato/Sylvester/chap27.html
United States: Biographical Directory of the United States Congress. John W. Taylor, 1784-1854. 11 December 2009 http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=T000091
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Scope and Content Note
The John W. Taylor Papers consist primarily of correspondence received by John W. Taylor in his capacity as a Congressional Representative of New York State from 1813-1833. The correspondence is generally of a political nature reflective of the germane issues of the period including western expansion, the anti-slavery movement, tariffs, banking, elections, the post office, and personal matters. Notable correspondents include Henry Clay, DeWitt Clinton, Alfred Conkling, Edward Everett, Jonathan Fisk, John B. C. Lucas, Henry C. Martindale, John McLean, Charles Miner, Hezekiah Niles, Eliphalet Nott, John Savage, Ebenezer Sage, Ambrose Spencer, James Tallmadge,Jr., Daniel D. Tompkins, Martin Van Buren, Daniel Webster, Hugh White, William Woodbridge and Samuel Young.
There is also correspondence from Taylor in draft or copy format as well as over 80 letters from Taylor to his wife, Jane Hodges Taylor. Other materials include speeches, governmental documents including resolutions, committee lists, notes and rosters, financial documents including receipts, stock certificates, mortgages, indentures and deeds, diplomas and certificates, personal notes, calling cards and invitations. The collection includes a land grant signed by James Monroe, an 1821 letter from Thomas Jefferson, and an 1819 epistle from the vintner John Adlum entitled Of the Cropogation of Vines.
Presidential Signatures
Presidential Signatures
Series 1 / Box 1 / Folder 1: Letter for John Quincy Adams, 1820
Series 1 / Box 2 / Folder 6: Letter from James Monroe, 1814
Series 1 / Box 3 / Folder 7: Entirely correspondence from Martin Van Buren
Series 1 / Box 4 / Folder 3: Letter from Thomas Jefferson, 1821
Series 4 / Box 5 / Folder 9: Land Grant signed by James Monroe
Related Archival Materials Note
The New Jersey Historical Society holds a small collection related to John W. Taylor including a hand-written genealogy.
Abolitionists -- United States.; Antislavery movements -- United States.; Ballston Spa (N.Y.); Broadsides (notices); Certificates.; Deeds.; Diplomas; Invitations.; Lawyers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Politicians.; Mortgages.; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government.; Receipts (financial records); Saratoga Country (N.Y.); Speeches (documents); Stock certificates.; Visiting cards; United States -- Politics and government.; Clinton, DeWitt, 1769-1828; Monroe, James, 1758-1831; Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848; Martindale, Henry C., 1779?-1860; Lucas, John B. C. (John Baptiste Charles), -1842; Niles, Hezekiah, 1777-1839; Fisk, Jonathan, 1778-1832; Conkling, Alfred, 1789-1874; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865; Young, Samuel, 1779-1850; Woodbridge, William, 1780-1861; Spencer, Ambrose, 1765-1848; Nott, Eliphalet, 1773-1866; Tallmadge, James, Jr.; Miner, Charles, 1780-1865; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852.; McLean, John, 1785-1861; Sage, Ebenezer, 1755-1834; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Tompkins, Daniel D., 1774-1825; Union College (Schenectady, N.Y.); United States. Congress
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1812-1847 (Box 4, Box 3, Box 2, Box 1)
  Arrangement Note
  Series 1: Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Content Note
  Series 1 consists of two subseries. Subseries 1 contains correspondence received by John W. Taylor primarily through the years of 1813-1833 while he served in Congress. The letters address a range of local, state and federal political issues including elections, political parties and abolition. Subseries 2 consists of draft or copy forms of correspondence created by John W. Taylor. This subseries includes over 80 letters to his wife, Jane Hodges Taylor from 1813-1833 that document a somewhat more intimate reflection on his day-to-day political life. Also in Subseries 2 is a draft of Taylor's letter sent to and the response received from Thomas Jefferson. While Jefferson declines knowledge of Taylor's request for information about Phi Beta Kappa, he does offer an unsolicited, somewhat cryptic but supportive in tone recognition of Taylor's political endeavors presumably with regard to his abolitionist stance. In light of Jefferson's acknowledged concern of the impact of the abolitionist movement upon the cohesiveness of the Union and his publicly neutral stance regarding the Missouri Compromises, this is an intriguing aspect of the collection.
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence received by John W. Taylor, 1812-1847 (Box 3, Box 1, Box 2)
    - Adams - Attwater, 1813-1830 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bailey - Booge, 1813-1840 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Booth - Burch, 1813-1842 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Campbell - Clark, 1813-1832 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Clay - Conkling, 1816-1830 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cook - Cushman, 1812-1830 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Davis - Dwight, 1814-1830 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Easton - Everett, 1817-1833 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Fenton - Freeman, 1813-1840 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Gales & Seaton - Gue, 1813-1840 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Haines - Hebb, 1820-1840 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Hendricks - Judah, 1814-1846 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Keeler - Knickerbacker, 1813-1833 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lane - Lucas, 1813-1840 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - McArthur - McMaster, 1815-1846 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Maris - Nott, 1813-1835 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Ostrander - Preston, 1813-1847 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Reed - Rush, 1814-1841 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Ebenezer Sage, 1813-1833 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - St. John - Spafford, 1814-1845 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Spencer - Swift, 1813-1841 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Taney - Turner, 1812-1838 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - James Tallmadge, 1813-1828 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - John Taylor, 1813-1825 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Daniel D. Tompkins, 1812-1820 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Upham - Vinton, 1814-1846 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Martin Van Buren, 1813-1816 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Watrous - Willard, 1814-1832 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Wilmer - Wright, 1816-1832 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Yates - Youngblood, 1813-1840 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 2: Correspondence from John W. Taylor, 1812-1841 and Undated (Box 4)
    - Adams - Crawford, 1812-1835 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - DeFouch - Granger, 1819-1833 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Harris - Nott, 1814-1845 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Paine - Swift, 1812-1834 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Tallmadge - Young, 1814-1836 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Unknown, 1820-1832 and Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - John W. Taylor letters to his wife, Jane Taylor, 1813-1821 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - John W. Taylor letters to his wife, Jane Taylor, 1822-1833 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series 2: Speeches, 1800-1839 (Box 5)
  Series 2: Speeches is arranged chronically with the exception of two folders of undated material.
  Series 2 consists of manuscripts of speeches delivered by John W. Taylor. This includes his 1803 graduation address from Union College entitled An Oration on Human Happiness, a published address of 1831 offered at "The Convention of Republican Antimasonic Delegates", a range of commencement speeches as well as oration pertaining to political matters and ideology. This series contains approximately a dozen orations prepared for Fourth of July celebrations.
  - Speeches, 1800-1839 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Speeches, Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Fourth of July Speeches, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series 3: Governmental Documents, 1808-1832 (Box 5)
  Series 3: Governmental Documents is arranged chronologically.
  Series 3 consists of documents related to governmental functions including resolutions, meeting notes, decrees, constituent issues, election tallies, rosters and committee lists. There is an undated broadside announcing John W. Taylor's nomination for Congress and a copy of a constituent's 1829 request for a Revolutionary War veteran's pension benefit.
  - Congressional Documents, 1813-1827 and Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - State and Local Documents, 1808-1821 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Constituent Issues, 1812-1832 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Documents related to Elections, 1808-1813 and Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Rosters and Committee Lists, 1809-1830 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series 4: Financial Documents, 1798-1832 (Box 5)
  Series 4: Financial Documents is arranged chronologically.
  Series 4 consists of documents related to finance including a land grant signed by James Monroe, Taylor's Power of Attorney to his wife, Jane (Hodges) Taylor, business arrangements which include his father-in-law John Hodges, receipts, stock certificates, indentures and deeds.
  - Financial Documents, 1798-1832 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series 5: Personal Papers, 1803-1832 and Undated (Box 5, Box 7, Box 6)
  Series 5: Personal Papers is arranged chronologically. Of note, Series 5 contains 13 "bundles" of calling cards and invitations housed in Box 6. The wrappers of 8 of the original "bundles" of 13 bear annotation with dates and are thus arranged chronologically followed by the remaining 5 undated "bundles". The original wrapping materials are housed separately in Box 7 and arranged in the same order.
  Description of the original 13 bundles:
  8 bundles with outer markings: 1."Cards & Invitations, 1818 – 1819, 2 fep. (?), 15 Cong". White paper wrapper with "draft" of business letter regarding court proceedings of an indebted client dated Aug. 25, 1918 on the inside. Tied with pink ribbon. 2."Cards ???, Dec. 21 to Jan. 20. 1822". White paper wrapper. 3."Cards, 1 fefs. (?) 18th Congrefs, Dec. 1. 1823 to May 27. 1824 –". White paper wrapper. 4."Visits, 2 fep. (?) 20th Cong". White paper wrapper with pink ribbon. 5."1829, 1830". White paper wrapper. 6."Cards ?? 2 fep (?), 21 Cong. 1830-31". White paper wrapper tied with pink ribbon. 7."Cards of Visit, 1 fep (?) 22 Cong, 1831. 32". White paper wrapper tied with pink ribbon. 8."Cards, 2 fefs (?). 22 Cong, 1823 – 33". Tan paper wrapper tied with pink ribbon.
  5 bundles with no outer markings: 2 bundles in white paper wrappers tied with pink ribbon. 1 bundle in tan paper wrapper tied with thin brown twine. 1 bundle wrapped in tissue paper tied with pink ribbon. 1 bundle in white paper wrapper on the inside of which there is a list of foreign dignitaries.
  Series 5 consists of diplomas and certificates, personal notes, invitations and calling cards. There is Taylor's 1803 diploma from Union College, several certificates attesting to Taylor's law credentials and a certificate declaring Taylor a Deputy Post Master. There is a series of undated papers which appear to be Taylor's notes and musings related to political activities. There is a substantial collection of calling cards spanning the years Taylor held office in Washington.
  - Diplomas and Certificates, 1803-1827 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Notes, Undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Invitations, 1805-1835 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Calling Cards and Invitations, 1818-1819 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Calling Cards, 1821-1822 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Calling Cards, 1823-1824 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Calling Cards, ca. 1827-1829 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Calling Cards, 1829-1830 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Calling Cards, 1830-1831 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Calling Cards, 1831-1832 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Calling Cards, 1832-1833 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Calling Cards, Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Calling Cards, Undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Calling Cards, Undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Calling Cards, Undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Calling Cards and Invitations, Undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Wrapping Materials for Calling Card Bundles, 1818-1832 (Box 7)